Guide to the Day Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Day family papers
1767-1929
MS 175
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
25.83
(60 boxes)
The Day family papers consist of correspondence, account books, diaries, journals, lectures, manuscripts, notes, sermons, and related papers of the Day family, 1767-1929. The personal lives, academic activities, and professional careers of several family members are documented, including Reverend Jeremiah Day (1737-1806), Reverend Jeremiah Day (1773-1867), Henry Noble Day (1808-1890), Mills Day (1783-1812), and others.
Day family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of children of Thomas M. Day, 1929. Gift of Harold L. Leupp, 1936. Gift of Sherman Day and Henry V. Day, 1939. Gift of Emma Thacher, 1943. Gift of Schaffer Library, Union College, 1988. Gift of Anne Day Thacher, 2003. Gift of Thomas Mcfadden, 2016.
Arrangement
Arranged in ten series and three additions: I. Correspondence, 1795-1905. II. Jeremiah Day, (1737-1806). III. Jeremiah Day, (1773-1867). IV. Thomas Day, (1777-1855). V. Thomas Mills Day, (1817-1905). VI. Henry Noble Day, (1800-1903). VII. Mills Day, (1783-1812). VIII. Jeremiah Day, (1773-1867): Presidential Papers, 1805-1860. IX. Marble Family, 1815-1845. X. Miscellaneous, 1789-1929.
Biographical / Historical
The Day family of Connecticut traces its American origins to Robert Day (1604-1648), who settled in Massachusetts in 1634 and shortly thereafter relocated in Connecticut. Several generations of family members, many of whom are represented in this collection, were educated at Yale University and later taught or held administrative positions there. Many family members chose a religious career, including Jeremiah Day (1737-1806), Jeremiah Day (1773-1867), Henry Noble Day (1808-1890), and Mills Day (1783-1812). Brief genealogical charts for the families of Jeremiah Day (1737-1806) and Thomas Day (1777-1855) are located here.
Scope and Contents
The Day family papers consist of correspondence, account books, diaries, journals, lectures, manuscripts, notes, sermons, and related papers of the Day family, 1767-1929. The personal lives, academic activities, and professional careers of several family members are documented, including Reverend Jeremiah Day (1737-1806), Reverend Jeremiah Day (1773-1867), Henry Noble Day (1808-1890), Mills Day (1783-1812), and others.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Other Finding Aids
For a listing of correspondents with the Day family, please consult the Correspondents Index.
Families; Religion; Women -- United States; Connecticut -- Economic conditions; Connecticut -- Politics and government; Europe -- Description and travel; Middle East; Account books; Diaries; Sermons; Clergy; Andrews, Catherine Day, 1819-; Baldwin, Henry, 1780-1844; Baldwin, Roger S. (Roger Sherman), 1793-1863; Baldwin, Simeon, 1761-1851; Bushnell, Horace, 1802-1876; Coit, Samuel Tracy, 1790-1848; Coit, Wheeler, 1739-1796; Daggett, David, 1764-1851; Dana, James, 1735-1812; Day, Abigail Noble, 1740-1810; Day, Charles, 1818-1890; Day, Daniel Jones, 1806-1883; Day, Ellen, 1829-1850; Day, Henry Noble, 1808-1890; Day, Jane Louisa Marble, 1809-1893; Day, Jeremiah, 1737-1806; Day, Jeremiah, 1773-1867; Day, Jeremiah, 1810-1874; Day, Mills, 1783-1812; Day, Noble, 1779-1855; Day, Sarah Coit; Day, Sherman, 1806-1884; Day, Thomas Mills, 1817-1905; Day, Thomas, 1777-1855; Dwight, James, 1784-1863; Edwards, Jonathan, 1745-1801; Ely, Mary Day; Foot, Samuel Augustus, 1780-1846; Holley, Alexander H. (Alexander Hamilton), 1804-1887; Holley, Sarah Day, 1814-1899; Lord, Hezekiah, 1740-; Lord, Sybel Coit, 1779-; Page, William, 1779-1850; Parker, Daniel, 1774-1834; Porter, Noah, 1781-1866; Putnam, Harriette Day, 1821-1894; Seymour, Elizabeth Day, 1816-1900; Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864; Staples, Seth Perkins, 1776-1861; Tallmadge, Benjamin, 1754-1835; Thacher, Elizabeth Day, 1820-1858; Trumbull, Benjamin, 1735-1820; Trumbull, Jonathan George Washington, 1789-1853; Webster, Noah, 1758-1843; Day family; Marble family; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- History; Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale University -- Students
- Correspondence, 1759-1905; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains letters of Day family members, with the bulk of correspondence relating to Thomas Day. The letters are largely personal in nature, relating to family concerns, although Thomas Day's activities as secretary of state in Connecticut are noted. Thomas Day's six daughters exchanged letters from the 1830s to the 1860s. His son, Thomas Mills Day, wrote often from Europe and the Middle East during 1850-1851.
  The earliest letters in the collection appear to be written to and by Reverend Jeremiah Day (1737-1806), a minister in New Preston, Connecticut, and the letters relate to religious topics and include items exchanged with Jonathan Edwards (the younger).
  - 1759 -1801 September (Box 1, Folder 1 - 18)
  - 1801 October -1805 December (Box 2, Folder 19 - 35)
  - 1806 January -1808 June (Box 3, Folder 36 - 50)
  - 1808 July -1810 July (Box 4, Folder 51 - 67)
  - 1810 August -1812 May (Box 5, Folder 68 - 85)
  - 1812 June -1815 July (Box 6, Folder 86 - 105)
  - 1815 August -1820 May (Box 7, Folder 106 - 123)
  - 1820 June -1831 April (Box 8, Folder 124 - 144)
  - 1831 May -1835 March 29 (Box 9, Folder 145 - 161)
  - 1835 March 29 -1840 March (Box 10, Folder 162 - 176)
  - 1840 April -1846 July (Box 11, Folder 177 - 191)
  - 1846 August -1850 April (Box 12, Folder 192 - 205)
  - 1850 May -1854 February (Box 13, Folder 206 - 219)
  - 1854 March -1863 August (Box 14, Folder 220 - 235)
  - 1862 January -1905 (Box 15, Folder 236 - 252)
  - Day, Ellen -Seymour, Elizabeth Day, undated (Box 16, Folder 253 - 259)
- Jeremiah Day (1737-1806), Series II
  This series contains an estate inventory, journals, poems, sermons, and theological papers written by Reverend Jeremiah Day from 1759-1804, and includes other family papers from later dates. Jeremiah Day's sermons date from 1759-1804, and his theological papers include student papers written at Yale University in the 1750s.
  - Estate inventory, undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Journals, 1788, 1794 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Poems, 1788-1800 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Sermons, 1759-1801 (Box 17, Folder 4 - 8)
  - Sermons, 1802-1804 (Box 18, Folder 9 - 11)
  - Theological papers
    - Exercises at Yale, 1755 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Notes, undated (Box 18, Folder 13 - 14)
    - Miscellanea, 1828, undated (Box 18, Folder 15 - 16)
- Jeremiah Day (1773-1867), Series III
  This series consists of account books, diaries, journals, lecture notebooks, manuscripts of books, sermons, and other papers of Reverend Jeremiah Day dating from 1797-1838. Papers relating directly to Day's service as president of Yale are arranged in Series VIII. Jeremiah Day, (1773-1867): Presidential Papers, 1805-1860.
  Diaries contain information on the years 1797-1801 and journals focus on the years 1799-1802, with information through 1845. Lecture notebooks and outlines contain Day's thoughts on the subject "Natural Philosophy," while manuscripts for books such as An Introduction to Algebra ..., The Mathematical Principles ..., Treatise of Plane Trigonometry, Edwards on the Will, Self Determining Power of the Will, and others are included in this series. Sermons prepared and delivered by Reverend Day from 1799-1838 are also arranged here.
  - Account books, 1812-1867 (Box 19, Folder 1 - 4)
  - Bills, 1810-1845 (Box 19, Folder 5 - 6)
  - Diaries, 1797-1801 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Journals, 1799-1801 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Journals, 1802-1845, undated (Box 20, Folder 9 - 11)
  - Lecture notebooks ["Natural Philosophy"]
    - 1-11, undated (Box 20, Folder 12 - 14)
    - 12-36, undated (Box 21, Folder 15 - 21)
    - 37-50, undated (Box 22, Folder 22 - 24)
    - Outlines, undated (Box 22, Folder 25 - 27)
  - Manuscripts
    - Introduction to Algebra..., 1812-1814 (Box 23, Folder 28 - 33)
    - Introduction to Algebra..., 1812-1814 (Box 24, Folder 34 - 39)
    - Treatise of Plane Trigonometry, 1813-1824 (Box 25, Folder 40 - 43)
    - Edwards on the Will, 1839 (Box 25, Folder 44 - 46)
    - Edwards on the Will, 1839 (Box 26, Folder 47 - 53)
    - Edwards on the Will, 1839 (Box 27, Folder 54 - 55)
    - Self Determining Power of the Will, undated (Box 27, Folder 56 - 59)
    - Self Determining Power of the Will, undated (Box 28, Folder 60 - 61)
    - The Mathematical Principles..., 1816 (Box 28, Folder 62 - 65)
    - The Mathematical Principles..., 1816 (Box 29, Folder 66 - 67)
    - Cousin's Psychology [review], 1835 (Box 29, Folder 68)
    - Meteors, [ca. 1808] (Box 29, Folder 69)
    - Solar eclipse, 1811 (Box 29, Folder 70)
    - Miscellanea, undated (Box 29, Folder 71 - 72)
  - Notes
    - Theology [books A -E], 1837 (Box 30, Folder 73 - 75)
    - Miscellanea, 1837 (Box 30, Folder 76 - 78)
    - Miscellanea, undated (Box 31, Folder 79 - 80)
  - Sermons, 1799-1821 (Box 31, Folder 81 - 84)
  - Sermons, 1822-1838 (Box 32, Folder 85 - 88)
- Thomas Day (1777-1855), Series IV
  This series contains a small quantity of personal and financial material relating to Thomas Day, and includes records for the Hartford Grammar School, 1811-1834.
  - Account books, 1808-1834 (Box 33, Folder 1 - 2)
  - Essay: Connecticut, undated (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Estate records, 1813, 1854 (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Hartford Grammar School records, 1811-1834 (Box 33, Folder 5 - 6)
- Thomas Mills Day (1817-1905), Series V
  This series contains several account books (1852-1905) for Day as well as an eight volume group of diaries (1865-1871, 1875).
  - Account books, 1852-1898 (Box 34, Folder 1 - 4)
  - Account books, 1873-1905 (Box 35, Folder 5 - 8)
  - Account books, 1895-1905 (Box 36, Folder 9 - 10)
  - Diaries, 1865-1871, 1875 (Box 36, Folder 11 - 13)
  - Index Rerum, 1836 (Box 37, Folder 14)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 37, Folder 15)
- Henry Noble Day (1800-1903), Series VI
  This series contains account books (1800-1903), business papers (1824-1913), sermons (1833-1864), correspondence (1848-1849, 1863-1884), and other papers relating to Day and his family, including his wife Jane Louisa Marble Day.
  - Account books, 1800-1815, 1829-1854 (Box 38, Folder 1 - 4)
  - Account books, 1840-1858 (Box 39, Folder 5 - 8)
  - Account books, 1848-1857, 1862-1864, 1877-1903 (Box 40, Folder 9 - 12)
  - Account books, 1895-1900 (Box 41, Folder 13)
  - Autograph books, 1825-1837 (Box 41, Folder 14 - 16)
  - Bank records, 1851 (Box 41, Folder 17)
  - Bibliographies, 1834-1863, undated (Box 41, Folder 18 - 19)
  - Bibliography, undated (Box 42, Folder 20)
  - Business papers, 1824-1846 (Box 42, Folder 21 - 24)
  - Business papers, 1847-1855 (Box 43, Folder 25 - 32)
  - Business papers, 1855-1913, undated (Box 44, Folder 33 - 37)
  - Commonplace book, 1837-1838 (Box 44, Folder 38)
  - Expense book, 1825-1828 (Box 44, Folder 39)
  - Inventory of personal library, undated (Box 44, Folder 40)
  - Marriage certificates, 1837-1851 (Box 44, Folder 41)
  - Miscellaneous legal papers, 1854-1888 (Box 44, Folder 42)
  - Sermons
    - Index, 1833-1864 (Box 44, Folder 43)
    - Texts, 1833-1864 (Box 45, Folder 44 - 50)
  - Correspondence
    - 1848 January -1849 December, 1863 January -1866 November, 1848-1849, 1863-1866 (Box 46, Folder 51 - 55)
    - 1866 December -1884, n.d., 1866-1884, undated (Box 47, Folder 56 - 63)
  - Miscellanea
    - Account book, 1824-1845 (Box 47, Folder 64)
    - Building specifications, 1837 (Box 47, Folder 65)
    - Diaries, 1872-1901 (Box 47, Folder 66)
    - Estate inventory, 1940 (Box 47, Folder 67)
    - Lists of subscribers to American Education Society, undated (Box 47, Folder 68)
    - Map of New York City, undated (Box 47, Folder 69)
  - Memo book, undated (Box 48, Folder 70)
  - Music book, undated (Box 48, Folder 71)
  - Notes, undated (Box 48, Folder 72)
  - Poem, 1836-1838 (Box 48, Folder 73)
  - Reception lists, 1877 (Box 48, Folder 74)
  - Recipe books, undated (Box 48, Folder 75 - 76)
- Mills Day (1783-1812), Series VII
  This series contains account books, sermons, and other papers of Day, who graduated from Yale in 1803 and served as a tutor at Yale College.
  - Account books, 1801-1809 (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - "General Instruction" book, undated (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - Notes, undated (Box 49, Folder 3)
  - Sermons, 1806-1809 (Box 49, Folder 4)
- Jeremiah Day, (1773-1867): Presidential Papers, 1805-1860; Series VIII
  This series consists of correspondence, student papers and materials, notes, records, speeches, and other items documenting Day's academic career and presidency of Yale University (1817-1846). Additional papers of Jeremiah Day are arranged in Series III. Jeremiah Day, (1773-1867). For official records of the Yale University President's Office see the finding aid for YRG-2.
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1817-1860 (Box 50, Folder 1 - 7)
    - College discipline, 1822-1843, undated (Box 50, Folder 8)
    - Fund raising, 1830-1832 (Box 50, Folder 9 - 10)
    - Honorary degrees, 1817-1846, 1854, undated (Box 51, Folder 11 - 12)
  - Comments on students, 1819-1832, undated (Box 51, Folder 13)
  - Lists
    - Donations, 1822, undated (Box 51, Folder 14)
    - Philosophical apparatus, 1805-1810 (Box 51, Folder 15)
  - Marking books, undated (Box 51, Folder 16)
  - Notes [college disputes], 1817-1826 (Box 51, Folder 17)
  - Papers: American Education Society, 1819-1844 (Box 51, Folder 18)
  - Records
    - Checks, 1809-1855 (Box 51, Folder 19)
    - Leaves of absence, 1817-1839 (Box 51, Folder 20)
    - Land deed, 1807 (Box 51, Folder 20a)
  - Reports: term examinations, 1818-1846 (Box 52, Folder 21)
  - Speeches
    - Inaugural address of Theodore Dwight Woolsey, 1846 (Box 52, Folder 22)
    - Miscellanea, 1817, 1846, undated (Box 52, Folder 23)
  - Student petitions, 1818-1844, undated (Box 52, Folder 24)
- Marble Family, 1815-1845; Series IX
  This series consists of the papers of several members of the Marble family, who married into the Day family in the 1800s. Jane Louisa Marble Day, the wife of Henry Noble Day, and other family members are represented in this series.
  - Day, Jane Marble (1809-1893)
    - Altar diary, undated (Box 53, Folder 1 - 3)
    - Autograph book, 1824 (Box 53, Folder 4)
  - Marble, Adeline
    - Compositions, 1821-1822 (Box 53, Folder 5)
    - Miscellanea, 1822, undated (Box 53, Folder 6)
  - Marble, Marietta H. [autograph album], 1826 (Box 54, Folder 7)
  - Marble, Susan Bishop
    - Commonplace book, undated (Box 54, Folder 8)
    - Diary fragments (multiple authors including Adeline Marble?), 1815, 1820 (Box 54, Folder 9)
    - Grammar school papers, 1819, undated (Box 54, Folder 10)
    - Journals, 1820 (Box 54, Folder 11)
    - Notebook, undated (Box 54, Folder 12)
  - Thacher, Thomas Anthony: diary, 1843-1845 (Box 54, Folder 13)
  - Miscellanea
    - Grammar books of Henry Noble Day family, undated (Box 55, Folder 14)
    - Unidentified, 1833 (Box 55, Folder 15)
- Miscellaneous, 1789-1929, undated; Series X
  - Newspaper clippings, 1839-1886 (Box 56)
  - Photographs of Days, Undated (Box 56)
  - List of names, 1835 (Box 56)
  - U. S. Senate Journal (Box 56)
  - Miscellaneous, 1828-1929 (Box 56)
    - Oversize, Undated (Box 57)
- Additional Material, 1767-1802; Accession 1989-M-042
  This accession contains a series of sermons preached by Jeremiah Day.
  - Twenty-three sermons preached by Jeremiah Day at Danbury and New Preston, Connecticut, 1767-1802 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Additional Material, 1797-1878; Accession 2003-M-086
  This accession consists of papers related to various Day family members. The majority of the papers relate to Jeremiah Day (1773-1867) and generally consist of family correspondence concerning health and religion, while other letters relate to Jeremiah Day's presidencies of Yale College and Andover Theological School and his business interests. Other papers related to Jeremiah Day include a partial account book, bills, wills, and other financial documents. Finally, the accession includes correspondence among other Day family members including Henry Noble Day (1808-1890) and Thomas Day (1777-1855) and a booklet of religious reflections written by Jeremiah Day (1737-1806).
  - Day, Henry Noble (1808-1890), correspondence with Mills Day and Elizabeth Day, 1807-1808, 1853, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Day, Jane Louisa Marble (wife of Henry Noble Day), The Literary Remains of Martha Day: With Rev. Dr. Fitch's Address at Her Funeral; and Sketches of Her Character, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Day, Jeremiah (1737-1806), booklet of religious reflections, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Day, Jeremiah (1773-1867)
    - Account book [partial], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bills, wills, and financial documents connected to estate, 1826-1878, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence
      - American Tract Society, 1857-1858 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Appointment at Andover Theological School, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Day, Henry Noble, 1797-1848 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Day, Jeremiah and Abigail, 1797-1808 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Day, Mills, 1808-1810 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Day, Olivia (Jones), 1827-1835 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Day, Thomas, 1803-1852 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Jeremiah Day and Company [business letters], 1803-1810 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Presidency of Yale College, 1799-1863 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Miscellaneous family letters, 1858-1864 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Thomas Day (1777-1855), correspondence with Jeremiah and Abigail Day and Mills Day, 1801-1811 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Additional material, Circa 1845-circa 1849; Accession 2017-M-033 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  This accession consists of two carte-de-visites of Jeremiah Day (BA 1795), the president of Yale College from 1817 to 1846, and his wife, Olivia Jones Day.